בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is נב, nun bet, 52.
We pick up on the middle of נא עמוד ב nun aleph
amud bet at the two dots. Just to review some of the
highlights from yesterday because it was very important in terms of some
core גמרא Gemara about מנהגים, minhagim, although as we noticed then, it
certainly lacked a certain amount of being systematic about the issues, but
it raised a lot of important issues.
One issue that came up was the very question about where does
what is the binding nature of מנהגים minhagim and being bound about
it by the later generations. מר Mar quoted the פסוק pasuk of
שמע בני מוסר אביך, Shma bni musar avicha, which is a question,
does that mean it's binding from the פסוק pasuk in the כתובים?
Ktuvim? The point I made at the time was that it's a
way of giving expression to the idea that it's a fundamental sort
of core, almost not even even more than core value, core operating
principle of a religious traditional society, which is that you are bound
by tradition.
Anyway, that at least begins with opening that question about the nature
of what makes it binding. Then an important issue we raised was
also that story spoke about the children of the people who started
the מנהג, minhag, but it started with the fact about the מנהג
minhag of the place. And certainly there's a question about
מנהג אבות, minhag avot, one inherited through one's forebears as opposed to
מנהג המקום. minhag hamakom. מנהג המקום Minhag hamakom is the dominant concept
that one finds: מקום שנהגים, makom shenohagim, מקום שאינו נהגים, makom she-eino
nohagim, etc.
Although in that story you had the question about your fathers accepted
it upon themselves and we discussed how nowadays the whole idea that
we say, "oh well we follow מנהג אשכנז" minhag Ashkenaz or "we're
ספרדים, Sfaradim, we have מנהג ספרד" minhag Sfarad is some interesting hybrid
of that because we don't actually live in אשכנז Ashkenaz or in
ספרד, Sfarad, we're not but we sort of view ourselves as people
of that place in a sort of virtual sense, extended sense, even
though we're not of that place itself. But that is an interesting
question, the difference between מנהג אבות minhag avot and מנהג המקום, minhag
hamakom, especially also when מקומות mekomot stopped being uniform and stopped being
a polyglot of different practices and so on, which happened like in
Amsterdam after the
גירוש ספרד, Gerush Sfarad, that you had all these different types of
communities and you had more cosmopolitan realities as we have nowadays. Then
the other issue became the question about keeping your own מנהגים minhagim
in violation of the current reigning practice, which was very strongly against
the משנה Mishnah about חומרי מקום שהלך לשם, humrei makom shehalach l'sham,
and nevertheless the גמרא Gemara seemed to feel that under certain circumstances,
if it wasn't a concern of a slippery slope, you'd be allowed
to at least observe your own מנהג, minhag, maybe even actively overturn
the present ones, but certainly at least keep your own מנהג. minhag.
And how did that work with the משנה? Mishnah? It was not
clear, but by the end the גמרא, Gemara, at least for a
whole דף daf the גמרא Gemara ignored the question. By the end
the גמרא Gemara spoke about maybe special circumstances, if you're visiting from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל, Bavel, and because of the authority
of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that gives you the right to keep
your own מנהג minhag and not have to sacrifice them for the
sake of the people of בבל. Bavel. We will touch on that
issue momentarily, but that was just some of the core issues that
did come up, but at least by the end we were back
to the more basic value of respecting the מנהג minhag of the
place that you are currently
at, right, and then other issues came up as well, the role
of דעתו לחזור, da'ato lachazor, planning on returning, how much of a
factor that is as an independent factor. And also of course the
issue that comes up that I mentioned just in the ראשונים Rishonim
about a different status between first of all מנהג minhag and ניהוג,
nihug, about a custom as opposed to a הלכה halakhic practice where
it's not a custom, it's a consciously thing that this is not
demanded by the law but it's our custom, as opposed to no,
it's our practice, my people will often confuse the two nowadays, "oh
it's my מנהג minhag to do חלב ישראל." Chalav Yisrael. Well maybe
it's your מנהג minhag if you think it's really not the הלכה,
halakhah, but sometimes what you really mean is that that's the פסק
psak that I'm following.
And
to think of those differences, and then there's a difference also therefore
if somebody is doing a practice because they think it's the הלכה
halakhah and they're mistaken, so that's actually a practice בטעות, b'ta'ut, and
that would be something that you might be more licensed to
actively sort of negate and undermine and overturn. Also there's something called
the מנהג שטות, minhag shtut, which again not a concept directly articulated
as such in the גמרא, Gemara, but an idea that this might
be a custom but it's nonsense, maybe it's even worse than nonsense,
maybe it potentially leads to other הלכה halakhic problems like taking from
the דאורייתא d'oraisa on the wheat, and that would also be a
scenario where it might be a special license not to try to
overturn that and negate that מנהג. minhag. Of course who gets to
determine that something is a טעות ta'ut or a שטות shtut is
another very interesting question. And the very last thing, so a lot
of important things yesterday, and the very last thing we saw was
the idea more about פסק psak than about מנהג, minhag, but if
that somebody is following a more innovative פסק... psak... have this idea
that like maybe you can rest on the authority of the person
who's doing it if you directly heard it from that person, but
if you didn't directly hear it from that person,
maybe it's harder to be seen as part of that chain of
tradition. So there was an idea of tradition more related to the
world of פסק psak which was very interesting because it's not normally
the way we operate. Somebody writes their פסק psak and then you
rely on their authority, even in later generations. Okay, let's now continue
in the middle of נ"א עמוד ב Nun Alef Amud Bet where
we move on in the משנה mishna about going about this principle
about you going from one place to the other, you keep the
חומרות chumros of where you came from, where you went from. And
then it says, but don't change things, keep as respect the practices
of the place מפני המחלוקת. mipnei hamachlokes.
So the גמרא gemara says like this: הולך ממקום, holech mimakom, יצא
ממקום, yatzah mimakom,
literally about halfway down, maybe forty percent from the bottom, twelve, fifteen
lines. בשלמא, bishlama, הולך ממקום שעושים למקום שאין עושים, holech mimakom she'osim
l'makom she'ein osim,
I get the case if you go from a place where they
do מלאכה melacha on ערב פסח Erev Pesach in the morning to
a place where they don't do מלאכה, melacha, נותנים עליו חומרי מקום
שהלך לשם, nosnim alav chumrei makom shehalach l'sham,
you keep the practices of the place that you are now visiting
and therefore you do not do מלאכה melacha on ערב פסח. Erev
Pesach. והרי שנה מפני המחלוקת, veha'rei shana mipnei hamachlokes, so A you're
keeping the חומרות, chumros, you're refraining from מלאכה, melacha, and B you're
not doing different from the reigning
norms, avoiding fights because you're doing what the people here are doing.
So when you keep the practices of a place you're in and
it's a חומרא, chumra, everybody is happy. מפני המחלוקת, mipnei hamachlokes,
and you won't do מלאכה. melacha. אלא ממקום שאין עושים למקום שעושים,
ela mimakom she'ein osim l'makom she'osim, but in the reverse case, where
you're coming from a place that doesn't do מלאכה melacha and you're
going to a place that does מלאכה, melacha, אל ישנה אדם מפני
המחלוקת, al yeshaneh adam mipnei hamachlokes,
if you really held of the principle of don't do things differently
because it'll lead to fights, so ונעביד, v'na'aveid, so you should do
מלאכה. melacha. הא אמרת, ha amart, נותנים עליו חומרי מקום שיצא משם,
nosnim alav chumrei makom sheyatza misham,
but you said you're bound by the stringencies of where you came
from. So those are contradictory. You can't tell me keep with the
practices of the place you came from and don't act differently from
the practices of the place that you're in. So how can I
be keeping the practices of the place I came from if those
are חומרות? chumros? הא אמרת, ha amart, נותנים עליו חומרי מקום שהלך
לשם, nosnim alav chumrei makom shehalach l'sham, וחומרי מקום שיצא משם, v'chumrei
makom sheyatza misham, or did I not end the
sentence?
Didn't you tell me you have to keep the חומרות chumros of
the place that you came from? So how could you do that?
It's in violation of the practices of this place. So אמר אביי
הרישא. amar Abaye ha reisha. So אביי Abaye says you're right, really
that idea of keep the peace, that's only in the first
case. That's why you keep the חומרות chumros of the place you're
visiting for the principle of keep the peace. But if you actually
are your place, your hometown is the one with the חומרות, chumros,
then forget about peace, keep your own חומרות. chumros. So according to
אביי, Abaye, it's actually interesting. When there's a conflict between those two
principles, keep the חומרות chumros of my hometown or keep the peace
here, it's more important for me to keep the חומרות chumros of
my hometown. אביי Abaye says, you're right, this line, the value of
keeping the peace is why you respect the חומרות chumros of the
place you're visiting. Those aren't your
חומרות, chumros, you're ספרדי, Sefardi, you're here now in אשכנזי Ashkenazi territory,
they have this crazy thing of not eating rice on פסח. Pesach.
So you're not really bound by their practice of not eating rice,
but why do you do it? Keep the peace, מפני המחלוקת. mipnei
hamachlokes. That's keeping the חומרות chumros of the place you're in. That's
the value there. But if you're actually it's your חומרות, chumros, you're
אשכנזי Ashkenazi and you're visiting ספרדי, Sefardi, what's more important is keep
your practices, and
that's more important, observing your own חומרות, chumros, than the keeping the
peace of the place you're in. That's what אביי Abaye says, which
is very interesting. רבא אמר, Rava amar, so this difference here interpreting
of the משנה mishna is a huge difference in terms of the
question of which value, which principle reigns supreme. אביי Abaye says when
it's between your practices and keeping the peace, your practices win out.
Why did we assume that not doing מלאכה melacha is somehow considered
very contentious?
Well, that's what רבא Rava is going to say. רבא אמר לעולם
הסיפא. Rava amar l'olam haseifa. רבא Rava says no, even in the
second case where you're going to a place that does מלאכה, melacha,
you can be keeping the peace. How could you be keeping the
peace? You're keeping your practices and you're not doing מלאכה. melacha. והכי
קאמר, v'hachi ka'amar, this is what it means: אין בזו מפני שינוי
המחלוקת. ein b'zo mipnei shinui hamachlokes. Yes, the reigning principle is keep
the peace, but you don't have to be concerned that in this
case that keeping your חומרות chumros will lead to a debate. Why?
מאי קאמרת? mai ka'amart? What will you say? הרואה אומר מלאכה אסורה?
ha'roeh omer melacha asura? That somebody is going to see you not
doing מלאכה melacha and go, 'Look at this guy, he thinks you're
not allowed to do מלאכה' melacha and it's going to lead to
a fight? No, you don't have to worry about that. אימר, eimar,
people aren't going to say you're not doing anything because you think
it's forbidden. So fey, כמה בטלני הוי בשוקא, kama batlanei havi bishuka,
there are a lot of lazy people that are in the marketplace.
Oh, you're staying at home ערב פסח erev Pesach watching TV? Nobody's
going to think oh look she thinks she's so פרום. frum. They'll
just think you're, you know, you're a lazy guy. And therefore it's
not a problem. Actually, where the הלכה halacha is brought down it
says that if you do this, you go from מקום שאינו עושים
makom she-einu osim to מקום שעושים, makom she-osim, you shouldn't do מלאכה,
melacha, but you have to be careful that you're not making it
obvious that you're doing it because you're of your מנהג. minhag. So
like if somebody, you know, asks you, hey, could you, whatever, could
you come help me mow the lawn? You can't say oh no,
no, no, I'm not, you know, whatever, I can't, that's not my
מנהג minhag or whatever. You have to have some other excuse, like
I'm in the middle of watching the ballgame. They really get upset
at you. Anyway, so,
so anyway, right, מפני המחלוקת. mipnei hamachlokes. But what's important is that
according to רבא, Rava, that is actually the more important principle. And
תוספות Tosafos says this explicitly.
And the הלכה halacha would actually be, if you go from a
place that has certain מנהגים minhagim to another place, even if for
some reason your places are, let's say for example, it's not a
חומרא chumra versus a קולא. kula. Let's say, I don't know, it's
a question of like נוסח התפילה. nusach hatefilla. Okay, I'll go this,
a question about if people would hear you or not, why they
hear you say, somehow you're a שליח ציבור. shliach tzibbur. Okay, and
it's, you're ספרדי Sefardi and you have to be a שליח ציבור
shliach tzibbur in an אשכנזי Ashkenazi שול shul or something of that
nature. It's not a question of חומרא chumra or קולא. kula. The
reigning principle is, it's more important to keep the peace than to
keep your own מנהגים. minhagim. Okay? Or even in a case where
it would really be a חומרא. chumra. Your own מנהגים minhagim are
more מחמיר, machmir, but somehow in the present context you can't do
it as a way that it just looks like you're being lazy
or whatever. To actually be keeping your practices would actually run in
the face of your חומרא chumra practices, in the face of the
current מנהגים. minhagim. According to רבא, Rava, when you can't do it
as a way that it doesn't look like a conflict, it'll be
obvious that you're, that you're keeping your own practices, you're actually supposed
to respect, more give weight to the practices of the place that
you're in. Now the question becomes, what about the example that I
started with? Something like I'm visiting, you know, I'm visiting ספרדים Sefardim
and it's, you know, and, and they've got this, you know, and,
and am I really supposed to eat rice on פסח Pesach because
I'm spending the whole פסח Pesach by my ספרדי Sefardi relatives in
a heavy ספרדי Sefardi community? So, you know, there are, then that's
where distinctions start becoming to be made within הלכה, halacha, where some
מנהגים minhagim are given much, much more weight than others. מנהגים minhagim
that are, you know, that are safeguards, like actually we saw yesterday
around certain halachic concerns, like the rice issue is. And also it's
hard to quantify it's not just that it's a safeguard. But you
know, for אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, eating rice on פסח Pesach is much different
than other types of things, which is like, you know, which is
done as a safeguard, but doesn't feel as halachic. You know, for
most אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, like not to eat rice on פסח Pesach feels
like a violation of פסח. Pesach. It doesn't feel just like, like,
you know, I haven't been observing my מנהג minhag or some type
of a thing. So it's very hard to quantify some of these
issues. And פוסקים poskim try, they try to particularly say that things
that are about protection of איסור issur have greater weight than things
that are סתם מנהגים. stam minhagim. Like, you know, to do כפרות
kapparot is different than not to eat rice, rice on פסח. Pesach.
But nevertheless, it is hard to quantify, and we don't always say
this. But at least there are מנהגים, minhagim, and it goes to
the other issues I said as well, which is how much does
מחלוקת machlokes apply nowadays when we live in a more cosmopolitan or
polyglot community? So if I'm visiting, you know, somebody here in Riverdale's
house and they happen to be ספרדי, Sefardi, I can't say אל
ישנה מפני המחלוקת. al yishaneh mipnei hamachlokes. The very nature of the
community is a multi-practice community, and it's not like there's a reigning
dominant thing and to do this makes me sort of in contention
with the whole community. But you could imagine I go to certain
places which are, you know,
which are the entire community is one type of a practice. And
then these issues really do apply. And according to רבא, Rava, that
is more important, אל ישנה מפני המחלוקת al yishaneh mipnei hamachlokes is
more important than חומרי מקום שיצא משם. chumrei makom she-yatza misham. Again,
with the recognition that there are some מנהגים minhagim that really stand
out as complete exceptions to that rule that are not treated as
just מנהגים. minhagim. Yes?
Right, but again, so sometimes it's not even a מחלוקת. machlokes. Let's
say you go to a ספרדי Sefardi place, they know אשכנזים Ashkenazim
have this, this thing.
נכון. Nachon. המחלוקת Machlokes isn't that they're ignorant. המחלוקת Machlokes is that
they're offended.
But who's going to be offended, let's say you're, you're ספרדי Sefardi
and, you know, so they know אשכנזים Ashkenazim don't eat rice.
Right. So that could be as well, meaning what you're saying is
taking the point of this sort of, of these sort of cosmopolitan
nature, it's true just more about our awareness. Our awareness is more
cosmopolitan so our ability to take offense about, you know, yeah, of
course you're doing because you're a crazy אשכנזי Ashkenazi that has these
crazy מנהגים. minhagim. So we all might think that you're crazy, but
nobody's taking offense. Right, that could be as well. And then that
sort of gives you less license of the מפני המחלוקת. mipnei hamachlokes.
There still could be cases where that isn't true, right, where people
are very, you know, you know, very, very serious about their things
and they, and they do take offense about them. Right.
But I mean, I'm sorry, you know, not rice but...
Well, they would call that a מנהג. minhag. But the example I
was giving to, yesterday, was try sitting and certainly in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael in a ספרדי Sefardi שול shul and cross... crossing your
legs. Oh my God, boom, yeah, they are like so offended by
that that you have to you have to respect, yeah, you're showing
your feet or something, anyway. So, yeah. All right, so that is
very yeah.
It occurred to me yesterday, like this is a particular aspect in
which I think there's a tension between creativity and consistency. Which as
we try to to apply these principles, right, as you say, even
the מחמיר machmir thought is confused about how, which where you apply
where, it's unclear. And what what you have to do, I think,
is what the ראשונים Rishonim do and and what
we continue to do in some cases, which is to deal with
new situations, you know, kind of based on principle. But principles are
always at cross purposes.
Right. I think that's well said, that these actually, you know, I
because there was a period where I'd try to do a lot
of research on מנהגים minhagim to get some type of a, you
know, clarity on when can you, you know, when can it fall
by the wayside, when can it override, when can you do this,
when can you do that. And right, it's all like guidelines. It's
nothing, they're right, like I was saying before, like we speak, some
פוסקים poskim will try to say, you know, if it's like מפני
איסורא, mipnei issura, חשש איסור, chashash issur, then you can, it gets
very heavyweight and you can't like ignore it or whatever. But again,
but some, yeah, and then because, and you know, and this this
is also מפני חשש איסור mipnei chashash issur some of this stuff
here, right, like being יוצא yotzei בקביעות, bikviut, you know, you know,
the גמרא Gemara about about the the brothers and all of that.
So, right, there's an attempt to try for some to quantify it,
but you're absolutely right. These were a lot of these operate more
as guidelines than as hard and fast rules. And given מנהגים minhagim
are given, you know, just at the grassroots level different types of
emotional and religious weight. So, yeah.
It just occurred to me, I think perhaps something of the same
tension is going on in these discussions
that pop up periodically, like about modernism and some
sort of maybe a sore spot.
But the tension between, between consistency and creativity.
Right. Absolutely. I remember I was asking, I once was, you know,
I had a חתן chatan and כלה kallah that didn't want to
do the badeken. So, you know, I figured or and or they
didn't want to do the badeken, they didn't want to do the
תנאים. tenaim. So, figured yeah, you know, come on, the תנאים tenaim
is just like it's just this מנהג, minhag, it has no הלכתי
halachic meaning whatever, blah blah blah. The תנאים tenaim is, you know,
when they sign this document during the חתן's chatan's טיש, tish, which
is an artifact of when the two sides of the חתן chatan
and כלה kallah used to used to used to like contract themselves
to to marry off their kids.
Not the כתובה. ketubah.
Anyway, whatever. So I was trying to get some clarity on like
which תנאי tenai can you use, which like מנהגים minhagim can you
just say, yeah, whatever, it's just a מנהג, minhag, you don't have
to do it, you know, would you say no, no, no, מנהג
minhag and are binding anyway. So I called up הרב יהודה הרצל
הנקין. Rav Yehuda Herzl Henkin. I wanted to get his input on
this and I was speaking to him about it and I said,
so like, you know, like so, you know, which מנהגים minhagim can
you like, you know, just say, yeah, it's just a מנהג minhag
we don't have to do it, especially because by the wedding thing,
it's like it's not like I've ever got married before, you know,
it's not like I personally have done this מנהג, minhag, but you
know, but okay, but you know. And he says, he said, yeah,
he said, I didn't do the תנאים tenaim at my wedding. I
said, okay, that's very nice, but what's the principle? He says, yeah,
you don't have to... he wouldn't give me an answer.
Anyway,
yeah.
רבקה? Rivka? It's a bit of open orthodoxy kind of
bit of...
Okay, oh god, we're going to get into that. But I think
it has those...
But think of visual how people come in dressed.
Right.
That's the issue about the balance between those... Right. Every
but that's the thing. All right. All right. Okay. All right. Every
but everyone receives עליות. aliyot.
Okay, fine. We got... all right. But that's exactly this, but that's
what I was saying about, but that was what I was saying,
yes, but things evolve. That's exactly what I was saying before, that
nowadays we wouldn't say to an אשכנזי Ashkenazi who goes to a
ספרדי Sephardi community, go ahead and eat rice, מפני המחלוקת, mipnei hamachloket,
because the nature of community has changed. Exactly the point that I
was saying that Michael was saying, a sense about what, you know,
the respect for diversity is a you know has really changed over.
Yes, it's a new, but it wouldn't not it doesn't legally contradict,
it's creates new norms, it creates new realities, you know. So the
issues of מחלוקת machloket have changed when we become more tolerant of
diversity. Yes.
It was a conversation about you know what kind of latitude does
a person have individually when he thinks just say a whole bunch
of מנהגים, minhagim, but he thinks one is a bit more הלכתי
halachic than the other? Do you get...
Yeah, again, like the good luck trying to find rules about these
things. Let's keep on reading a little bit more. אמר ליה רב
ספרא לרבי אבא, Amar lei Rav Safra le-Rabbi Abba, כגון אנא, kegon
ana, now you're going to really enjoy this example, now that we
spoke about not being משנה מפני המחלוקת, meshane mipnei hamachloket, okay, and
important to remember like רבא Rava basically is
emphasizes that that wins out over your personal חומרות, chumrot, although as
I said, when exactly to say this is not clear. Anyway, אמר
ליה רב ספרא לרבי אבא, Amar lei Rav Safra le-Rabbi Abba, כגון
אנא, kegon ana, like I, דידענא בקביעא דירחא, d-yidana b-kavia d-yarcha, I
know when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is. Right?
Why should I have to keep two days? I know when ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh is. בישוב... B-yishuv... Of like two days of ראש
השנה *Rosh Hashanah* or two days of, maybe that's not a good
example, two days of סוכות *Succos*, two days of פסח *Pesach*. בישוב
לא הוינא מאינש דעני מחלוקת machlokes *Be-yishuv lo havina me-inish de-inei machlokes*.
When I am in a settled, you know, in the settlement, not
out in the wilderness, then I don't do מלאכה melacha, *melacha* on
the second day because I don't want to, you know, lead to
fights and debates. במדבר מאי *Bamidbar mai*? What about if I'm out
in the wilderness and I'm not, you know, I'm not in a
town and can I keep, do I have to keep the second
day יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*? So אמר ליה Amar lei,
*amar lei*, הכי אמר רבי Rebbi אמי *hachi amar Rabbi Ami*, this
is what רבי Rebbe, אמי *Rabbi Ami* says. בישוב אסור *Be-yishuv assur*,
yes, in a settled town you cannot do מלאכה melacha, *melacha* on
the second day יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*, ובמדבר מותר *u-vamidbar
mutar*, but out in the wilderness you're allowed. Now, what does this
mean? תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*, now תוספות *Tosafos* says nowadays we all know
קביעא דירחא *kvi'ah de-yarcha*, we all know when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
*Rosh Chodesh* really is and we still keep two days יום טוב
Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*. So תוספות *Tosafos* says, and the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says that explicitly, we know when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh
Chodesh* is and we still keep two days. So what makes him
special? So תוספות *Tosafos* says he really wasn't saying, although this is
a forced read in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, that just he knew
when ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* was. What he actually is saying is
I am from one of the places near Israel that was always
informed when ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* was. Because according to the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, actually the line of difference between one day and two
days is not just ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. *Eretz Yisrael* versus out
of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*. It's Israel and all the
places that could have been informed in enough time, right, within fifteen
days or fourteen days or whatever from ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh*. Those
places keep one day. Places that couldn't have been informed in enough
time they keep two days. So תוספות *Tosafos* says what he actually
is saying is it's like he's saying I was from Israel. He's
saying I'm from a place that only keeps one day. He didn't
actually say that, it's a little bit of a hard read. But
then, now I'm when I'm visiting the places in בבל Bavel *Bavel*
that keeps two days, what do I do? So according to this
though, so let's grant that point, but according to this though, if
you have a person from Israel visiting in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz
*Chutz La-aretz*, does he have to keep one day or two days?
So it says if you're בישוב *be-yishuv* two days, if you're במדבר
*bamidbar* one day, because of respecting the practices of the place. So
actually though, there's an interesting debate in the פוסקים poskim *poskim* which
is the issue of, what do you call it, of what about
if you're here, you know, you're here in town, you're בישוב *be-yishuv*,
no, no, no, forget דעת לעקור *da'as la-akor*, of course we're dealing
with דעת לחזור Daas Lachzor *da'as lachazor*. But you're going to do
it בצנעה *be-tzina*. Here I am, I'm an Israeli, I'm visiting here,
I'm not out in the wilderness, I'm not somewhere, you know, in
the forest or I'm not even in a town of non-Jews, I'm
here in a Jewish community for יום טוב Yom Tov? *Yom Tov*,
but on the second day can I at least do מלאכה melacha
*melacha* in private that nobody sees me? So there's actually a debate
of the פוסקים poskim *poskim*, some say yes, some say no. There
are some Israelis that definitely that מר סבר *mar savar* is בצנעה
*be-tzina*. No, but אם חבירו יודע בו *im chaveiro yodeia bo*?
No, but the whole point, that's a good point, but the whole
point here is that it's
a מפני המחלוקת *mi-pnei machlokes* issue. It's not a looks
like you're doing something אסור *assur*. Nobody thinks you're doing something אסור
*assur*. People understand you're an Israeli, they just take offense. So it's
not a מראית עין *maris ayin*. Because מראית עין *maris ayin* is
they think you're doing something אסור *assur*. Okay? But anyway, so there
is that debate. The reality is, is that a lot of, you
know, times I do know sometimes some Israelis will be מקפיד *makpid*
and do it בצנעה *be-tzina*. But a lot of times they just
go ahead and they just do מלאכה melacha *melacha* on יום טוב
שני Yom Tov Sheni. *Yom Tov Sheni*. And you know, it's, you
know, a lot of people take like strong offense, 'Oh, you're not
supposed to, you have to keep two days,' you know, especially we
as, we as, you know, people חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz? *Chutz La-aretz*
are very מקפיד *makpid* on our two days יום טוב Yom Tov
*Yom Tov* somehow. You know, we're, because it undermines, anyway,
so you know, but to remember by the way that, you know,
we were just talking about before, everybody would assume that if you're
אשכנזי *Ashkenazi* visiting ספרדים *Sefardim*, you're going to keep your, your קטניות
Kitniyos *kitniyos* מנהג minhag. *minhag*. You know, if we say that things
have changed, that the מפני המחלוקת *mi-pnei machlokes* realities are different than
they used to be and we're more understand and tolerate diversity and
all of that, so you know, if an Israeli is here keeping
his one day, the only reason he would have to keep two
days is the מפני המחלוקת *mi-pnei machlokes* reality, right? So if we
just got through saying a minute ago that there's less of those
מפני המחלוקת *mi-pnei machlokes* issues nowadays, you know, then maybe that would
be an equal factor in terms of that type of a consideration.
I also want to remind you that yesterday we learned that if
you're visiting from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* to בבל *Bavel*,
right, you don't have to care as much about the מפני המחלוקת
*mi-pnei machlokes* issue because you're more of the position of religious authority.
And there's some power to that nowadays, particularly about the one and
versus two day יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*. Because the one
day יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* we all know is the
real thing, right? And it's almost just like a good, almost like,
you know, it's a good advertisement for, you know, Jewish Agency should
send a lot of Israelis to keep one day יום טוב Yom
Tov. *Yom Tov* because it's like it's, you know, 'Oh my God,
if I was only living in Israel, I would only have to
keep one day יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*.' So you know,
the idea that they're keeping one day, on the one hand you've
got the מפני המחלוקת *mi-pnei machlokes*, but on the other hand you've
got this is the real thing, you know? So maybe they should
be entitled to keep one day in our presence to sort of,
you know, say, 'this is the real thing, why should I have
to follow your practice?' So it's interesting the way it brings up
those issues about are the realities of מפני המחלוקת *mi-pnei machlokes* different
or not, and particularly from ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* to בבל *Bavel*.
That's about Israelis coming to America as long as it's
דעת לחזור *da'as lachazor*, right?
Yeah, yeah, with all assuming דעת לחזור *da'as lachazor*. If it's not
דעת לחזור *da'as lachazor*, then you become like the place you're moving
to.
If you're here for like years?
I'm not getting into that discussion, okay, but I'm Assuming that we're
dealing with דעת לחזור. When it's not דעת לחזור and you're planning
on settling, then you become a citizen of the new place. I
want to just say one thing about the flip case, which is
from בבל to ארץ ישראל.
You're an American visiting Israel in יום טוב. Yom Tov Okay? So,
you know, when I... it used to be that like everybody said
you gotta keep two days יום טוב. Yom Tov. Except some crazy
Zionist פוסקים who said, "Oh no, it's so much... we're hoping that
you're going to stay," so you keep one day יום טוב, Yom
Tov right? Nowadays, I think it's much more prevalent to get a
פסק. psak. Some people say like a day and a half, you
don't do מלאכה, melacha but you
דאוון daven חול. chol. And there are definitely more and more פוסקים
that are saying that you keep only one day when you're visiting.
What is that about? Whatever happened to the idea of
חומרי מקום שיצא משם? chumrei makom she'yatzah mi'sham? So the חומרות chumras
of...
More flights, more direct flights. What? I think it was just more
direct flights and more disposable income.
Oh, so
therefore what? You want to encourage people to come for יום טוב?
Yom Tov, No, but no one takes a second day. I don't
know if they say it's pressure from the floor, like from people
who say, "Listen, it's ridiculous. I'm not going to tolerate this." Right.
Right. Or if it's recognizing a different reality as you're... Right.
Right. So you mean, oh, so it's just, yeah, okay.
But so there is no...
you
know, the מנהג המקום minhag hamakom is of a different nature. Right,
right, right. So things have changed. Maybe it's because of more direct
flights, more income, more people present. But I do want to say
what the logic is. Whatever happened to the חומרי מקום שיצא משם
chumrei makom she'yatzah mi'sham issue? So the חכם צבי Chacham Tzvi was
asked this question in a short beautiful little תשובה. teshuva. He was
the father of רב יעקב עמדין. Rav Yaakov Emden. So what generation
was he? He was 17th century? I think he was... what, early
18th?
Early 18th? Yeah, something like that. I'm trying to remember. Okay, anyway,
so
he... so anyways, what did he say? So he פסקנ'ד paskened the
following.
He said that first of all in terms of... in terms of
what נוסח nusach דאוונינג davening you say, he says you וודאי vadai
say נוסח nusach חול. chol. You can't say, "I'm being מחמיר machmir
and going to דאוון daven של יום טוב." shel Yom Tov. It's
not a חומרא. chumra.
Actually, it's a violation to דאוון daven יום טוב Yom Tov, when
it's a weekday. Here in Israel it genuinely is a weekday or
חול המועד Chol Hamoed or whatever it is. So to דאוון daven
של יום טוב shel Yom Tov is not a חומרא. chumra. To
דאוון daven של יום טוב shel Yom Tov is actually not doing
the right דאוונינג. davening. So certainly when it comes to דאוונינג, davening,
you know, you should דאוון daven של חול. shel chol. But he
says, or putting on תפילין... tefillin... I mean depending on if it's
like... people put on תפילין tefillin חול המועד Chol Hamoed or if
it's the last day יום טוב, Yom Tov, to not put it
on is not a חומרא chumra to, you know, because the reality
from the perspective of the is that you're חייב chayiv in תפילין.
tefillin. So to not put it on is... so that you've got
to do. What about not doing מלאכה, melacha right? According to this
גמרא Gemara right, you know, not doing מלאכה Melacha and so on.
So he says, he said that actually is not allowed for you
not to do מלאכה Melacha. and keep your חומרות. chumras. Why? Because
when do you keep your חומרות chumras in the place you're visiting?
That's where if you were living here, that would be an acceptable
practice. Okay, like if I was living here it would be acceptable
for me, forgetting מחלוקת Machlokes issues, it'd be acceptable for me not
to work on ערב יום טוב, erev Yom Tov, you know, like
ערב פסח. erev Pesach. It would be acceptable for me to, you
know, whatever the חומרות chumras here was, not to go in the
bathhouse with my brother. That would be acceptable, you know, if you
happen to be living here. He said but if you happen to
be living in Israel, it wouldn't be acceptable for you to refuse
to do מלאכה on the second day of יום טוב Yom Tov.
or on the last day after יום טוב. Yom Tov. What would
that be? Your refusal to do מלאכה would be בל תוסיף. bal
tosif. Okay, it really raises a question why second day יום טוב
Yom Tov. in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz, is not בל תוסיף. bal
tosif. Okay, but there at least it's because the rabbi somehow mandated
it. But if you're in a place where it's not mandated, to
choose to do it as treating it as a type of a
יום טוב Yom Tov is a type of a בל תוסיף. bal
tosif. Now a way to say that a little bit differently, which
I've heard the חכם צבי's Chacham Tzvi position reframed and this makes
it maybe even a little more understandable is, he says, "Look, we're
saying why do you keep two days in חוץ לארץ? chutz la'aretz,
It's because מנהג אבותינו בידינו." minhag avoseinu b'yadeinu. Had we been in
the time of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and you were living
in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz. so you would have kept two days
because you wouldn't have known when ראש חודש was. So let's imagine
nowadays we're living in the time of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
You're visiting from America to Israel. What would you have done in
the time of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Forgetting מנהג. minhag You
would have kept one day because in those circumstances you would have
known when ראש חודש was. So you're keeping מנהג אבותינו. minhag avoseinu.
The מנהג אבותינו minhag avoseinu is to do what you would have
done in the time of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So anyway,
that is his argument that he says that you actually keep only
one day, and it's a very persuasive argument. But nevertheless, a lot
of
people... yeah, I don't know, it's very persuasive, yes.
You just touched on maybe that's the answer as to why... as
to why we keep a second day because it's not a... for
us, right? That's the difference between a מנהג Minhag and a rabbinical...
so the גמרא's Gemara going to... The גמרא Gemara is going to
discuss that when it discusses two-day יום טוב. To treat it as
a מנהג Minhag, or to treat it as, here it's being treated
as a מנהג, Minhag but to treat it as a מנהג Minhag,
or to treat it as a תקנה Takana is a different מחלוקת
of different גמרות Gemaras today.
I know, the גמרא Gemara goes from one to the other, by
the way. I know, could be, yes. I think you are right.
I think it also goes back to like the rice issue, do
you know? Which is that number one, there's some גמרות Gemaras that
speak related to two days יום טוב more as a תקנה Takana
than as a מנהג, Minhag as a דרבנן. D'rabanan. And number two
is, it's like the same way, I mean, there are some Americans
that are very happy to drop קטניות Kitniyos, when visiting Israel. But
there are many that basically even if they're keeping only one day
יום טוב, still, God forbid, they wouldn't eat קטניות, right? So we
give different weights to different things. And keeping two days יום טוב,
you know, people, you know, at an emotional religious level, we feel
it's ממש, Mamash, it's like you know, this taboo, it's an איסור
מלאכה, Issur Melacha, קדושת יום טוב, Kedushas Yom Tov, and you know,
that creates this reality that all מנהגים Minhagim are not treated in
the same way. So I think that that's right. Okay, we have
to move on really because it's very late. Okay, so let's keep
on looking.
רב נתן בר אסיא Rav Natan bar Asya אזל מבי רב לפומבדיתא.
Azal m'bei Rav l'Pumbedita. So he went from the house of רב
Rav to פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. יום טוב שני של עצרת. Yom Tov Sheni
Shel Atzeret. It was the second day of יום טוב, okay, of
שבועות. Shavuot. So שמתיה רב יוסף. Shamsay Rav Yosef. So רב יוסף
Rav Yosef put him in חרם. Cherem. So אמר ליה אביי, Amar
lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, why was he? Why was he
doing it? He was violating יום טוב שני.
Oh, you mean what was the איסור? Issur?
Maybe they, right, yeah, no, there's definitely תחום, Techum, at minimum there's
a תחום Techum problem. I mean, maybe he did other things, but
yeah, sure, להפקעתא דתחום L'apkaiteh d'techum or about two days יום טוב.
Okay, minimally there's a תחום Techum issue, maybe well also יום טוב.
All right, so let's read the story. All right, we gotta hold
off on the comments because we're running out of time. So anyway,
אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, ולינגדיה מר
נגידי. Velingdeh mar nigidei. Why did you just put him in חרם?
Cherem? You should have given him lashes. אמר ליה, Amar lei, דטב
ליה עבדתי ליה. D'tav lei avidti lei. No, I did something better.
Better here meaning more stringent. Why? דבמערבא, D'vema'arava, because in ארץ ישראל,
מינו אנגידי, Minu a-nigidei, they would take a vote before giving lashes
דבר
בי רב D'bar bei rav when a rabbinic student, when a rabbi,
when somebody from the rabbinic class does something wrong, they'll take a
vote before doing lashes, ולא מינו אשמתא, V'lo minu a-shamta, but they
won't before putting somebody in חרם. Cherem. Now why does it mean
that חרם Cherem is worse? So רש"י Rashi basically says, I mean,
that or the way it's explained is that if you know, is
that חרם Cherem is such a, let me, one minute,
because they only do חרם Cherem on things that are very stringent.
And therefore, it's so pressing to respond to a stringent violation that
they won't take the time to first go ahead and do, and
you know, and do a vote. So therefore, I know, you could
have read it the opposite, but that's the way it's understood because
putting חרם Cherem is something
is what we do for stringent violations, and therefore we don't even
bother to vote about it, we just go ahead and do it.
איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say, נגדיה רב יוסף. Nigdih Rav Yosef.
So רב יוסף Rav Yosef gave him lashes. אמר ליה אביי, Amar
lei Abaye, ולשמתיה מר. V'lishamteih mar. Why didn't you put him in
חרם? Cherem? דרב ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו, D'Rav u'Shmuel d'amri t'vayu, משמתינן אשני
ימים טובים של גליות. Meshomtinan a-shnei yamim tovim shel galuyos. You put
somebody in חרם Cherem if they violate the second day of יום
טוב. אמר ליה, הני מילי איניש דעלמא. Hani mili inish d'alma. That's
a normal guy off the street.
הכא צורבא מרבנן הוא. Hacha tzurba miderabanan hu. Here he's a member
of the rabbinic class. דטב ליה עבדתי ליה. D'tav lei avidti lei.
That I did, I did something better to him, meaning I was
more lenient to him. דבמערבא מינו אנגדותא דבר בי רב ולא מינו
אשמתא. D'vema'arava minu a-nagiduta d'bar bei rav v'lo minu a-shamta. Again, the
same idea that somehow lashes is conceived to be a less stringent
punishment than חרם. Cherem. And therefore, I went a little bit easy
on him because he was only a rabbinic, because he was from
one of us. Now the point though being, I want to say
again, notice the shift. We're talking about second day יום טוב as
a מנהג and עשינה מפני המחלוקת, Ayishana mipnei hamachlokes, and then we
talk about, you know, giving somebody lashes or putting somebody in חרם.
Cherem. Presumably that's not the type of reaction you would expect if
somebody did מלאכה in the morning of ערב פסח Erev Pesach in
a place they don't do מלאכה. So it gets again to this
issue about not all מנהגים Minhagim are treated in the same way
and, you know, this point about it's hard to really pin down
any real rule. Yeah.
And not just מנהגים, Minhagim, it's not all people, not all Jews
are
treated as, right, exactly, that's true as well.
Now you would imagine we'd be stricter with,
well, that was the first answer, that we were stricter, we go
a little bit easier, right?
But
so, you know, we'll be stricter with everybody else, with our own
network. Right.
That, that is what it sounds like, unless again you read the
end story that it's reversing the sense of of whether lashes or
a חרם Cherem is more stringent. It could be. Anyway, yes, let's
keep on going. That is true. כיוצא בו. Kiyosei bo. המוליך פירות
שביעית. Hamolich peiros shevi'is. Now we sort of digress because the example
is a שמיטה Shemita example and that leads us to a whole
discussion about שמיטה. Shemita. So it says if you take שמיטה Shemita
produce from a place where the produce is no longer basically, you
know, you can collect apples in the field and bring them into
your house. But then when there's no longer any apples on the
trees even... For the wild animals, you have to take take all
what you have in your house and do ביעור, Biur, destruction, which
doesn't literally mean destroy it, means take it out of your house,
distribute it to the poor, distribute it to the animals, and so
on. So you took fruit, apples, from a place where there was
no longer apples on the tree, and you're now visiting a place
and you have your apples with you in a place where apples
are still on the tree, or vice versa. So it says you
do whatever—you always get rid of them because either back in your
hometown they're getting rid of them or where you are they're getting
rid of them. Okay. And רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says, no, you
can say, look, go bring the apples yourself. And what does go
bring the apples yourself mean? So רש״י Rashi says what it means
is the following and it's a very powerful argument. He says, this
isn't חומרי מקום שהלך לשם וחומרי מקום שיצא משם. chumrei makom shehalach
lesham vechumrei makom sheyatza misham.
What I would say to you, here I am, I'm visiting you,
there are no apples here in Riverdale, but you know there are
apples back in, I don't know, Ohio. Okay? And I'm visiting you
with my Ohio apples. Okay, for me to continue eating them is
not not respecting your חומרא, chumra, because I can say to you,
you know what, if you would import some Ohio apples you wouldn't
have to get rid of them either because they go by the
rules of where they're picked. You know, actually come have some of
my apples, you don't have to get rid of them. So it's
not a question of the מנהגים minhagim of this place, it's that
these—this food—is from a place that you don't—it's imported food that you
don't have to get rid of yet because it comes from a
place where there are apples still on the tree. So that—so that
seems like a very reasonable response. So the גמרא Gemara somehow doesn't
like it. So the גמרא Gemara says ולית ליה לרבי יהודה הא
דתנן דרבי יהודה לא סבירא ליה נותנין לו חומרי המקום שיצא משם
וחומרי המקום שהלך לשם, uleis lei leRebbi Yehuda haditnan deRebbi Yehuda lo
sovir lei nosein lo chumrei hamakom sheyatza misham vechumrei hamakom shehalach lesham,
that you go by both stringencies? So how can you just say,
oh look, you know, hey, the apples I got are from an
okay place. Here they're not eating apples. So אמר רב ששת בריה
דרב אידי מילתא אחריתא קאמר רבי יהודה. Amar Rav Sheshet brei deRav
Idi milsa achrita kaamar Rebbi Yehuda. You're right. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
wouldn't disagree that here you shouldn't be eating the apples. He's saying
something else. והכי קאמר. Vehachi kaamar.
This is what the משנה Mishna is saying, meaning the משנה Mishna
actually is missing a thing. Once again reading, like putting a line
into the משנה. Mishna. או ממקום שלא כלו למקום שלא כלו, O
mimakom shelo kalu lemakom shelo kalu, let's say you went from one
place that there are no apples to another place there are no
apples, neither place that there are apples. So שמע—so shama I'm sorry,
I'm sorry excuse me that it didn't finish—there are. Okay, I took
it from Ohio, I'm visiting here, in both places when I took
my apples from Ohio they were on the tree and here they're
on the tree. ושמע שכלו במקומו, Veshama shekalu bimkomo,
and then I got a report that now there are no apples
left on the trees back in Ohio, but here there still are
apples. So חייב לבער. chayav levaer. In that case, I have to
follow the, you know, the place I came from and I have
to get rid of the apples. That's what the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma say. Okay, רבי יהודה אומר צא והבא לך אף אתה מהיכא
דאייתינהו והלא לא כלו להו. Rebbi Yehuda omer tze vehaivei lach af
atah mehacha deaseinu vehalo lo kalu lehu. So רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
say no, you could say back to the place where you got
it from, you know, if you were to bring apples to this
place it wouldn't be a problem because here they're still around. Okay,
which is a little funny. But the basic point is look, when
I took apples from there, they were still on the tree.
So there was not yet a practice there not eating the apples.
Right now I'm here and here they're still eating the apples. So
why should it matter if back over there the practice has changed
during my absence? So the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, למימר דרבי יהודה לקולא קאמר? lomeimar deRebbi Yehuda lekulla kaamar?
That sounds like רבי יהודה'ס Rebbi Yehuda's being lenient. He says, hey,
you know, I can keep on eating because here they're at least
eating and when I left my old place they were still eating.
So גמרא says, אמר רבי אלעזר למימר דרבי יהודה לחומרא? Amar Rabbi
Elazar lomeimar deRebbi Yehuda lechumra? But רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says has
a tradition that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda was being מחמיר. machmir. Okay
אלא איפו. ela eifo. Okay fine, so read what's going on here
again in this invisible debate because it's not in the words of
the משנה, Mishna, read it the opposite. אינו
חייב לבער, Eino chayav levaer, you don't have to destroy it when
because you left the place you didn't have to destroy and now
and here there are still apples. Still the same case that when
in Ohio I left when they were on the tree and here
they're on the tree. But in the meantime they're no longer on
the tree in Ohio. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is saying
in that case you don't have to worry about it because when
you left it was okay and now it's still okay. רבי יהודה
אומר צא והבא לך אף אתה מהיכא דאייתינהו, Rebbi Yehuda omer tze
vehaivei lach af atah mehacha deaseinu, no, that's not true because if
you were now to be having apples back in Ohio, the place
I brought them from, והלא כלו להו, vehalo kalu lehu, there's no
longer on the tree. Okay, so it's a very complicated read in
the משנה, Mishna, but basically as opposed to reading רבי—the Rebbe. משנה—like
Mishna the פשוטה peshuta that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is saying a
very reasonable statement which is why should I have to follow the
practices of this place, it's not a question of the place, it's
a question of where the food comes from, is it Ohio food
or is it New York food, you know, fruit? But which—but the
גמרא somehow feels that no, somehow that would violate the principle of
חומרי מקום שהלך לשם chumrei makom shehalach lesham and therefore it makes
this whole issue a very special case that it started off okay
in both places and it changed in the interim. Okay, אביי אמר
לעולם דאייתינהו, Abaye amar leolam deaseinu, רבי—I'm Rebbe sorry, לעולם כדתנן, no,
don't have that whole read into the משנה, Mishna, read it the
simple way. והכי קאמר, Vehachi kaamar, that you went from a place
of—that was doing one practice to a place that was doing the
other. או ממקום שלא כלו למקום שכלו, O mimakom shelo kalu lemakom
shekalu, you took your apples from Ohio where they're still on the
tree and you brought them to New York where they're no longer
on the tree.
והחזירם למקומם, Vehachaziram limkomo, you
brought them back to Ohio, ועדיין לא כלו, veadai lo kalu, and
they're still on the tree in Ohio. So that you took them
from the tree in Ohio you were allowed to eat them, you
brought them to New York, in New York you weren't allowed to
eat apples, and then you took the same apples and you brought
them back to Ohio. Okay? So what would you think? Should you
be allowed to eat these apples? Yes. Yes. Okay, so אינו חייב
לבער, Eino chayav leva'er, you don't have to get rid of them.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, צא והבא לך אפצא מהיכא דאייתינהו.
Tze v'havi lach apatza meheicha d'aytinu. No, because if you were to
now, if you were to be importing apples from New York, you
wouldn't be able to eat them. You're not allowed to eat New
York apples. והוינהו הוא? V'havinhu hu? So these apples magically became New
York apples when I brought them into New York, even though they
didn't grow off of the New York trees. And now that I'm
bringing them back to Ohio, they remain New York apples. So the
Gemara says, so by the way, notice we're no longer talking about
חומרי מקום שהלך לשם, Chumrei makom shehalach l'sham, we're talking about some
weird idea of the apples changing their status for הלכות שביעית. Hilchos
Shevi'is. So מתקיף לה רב אשי, Matkif lah Rav Ashi, Rav Ashi
did not like this at all to Rabbi Yehuda. אטו אגבא דחמרא
קלטינהו? Atu agaba d'chamra kaltinhu? What, on the back of the donkey
they became absorbed into the city? Meaning, because the apples spent a
little time in New York, they transformed into New York apples? They're
still Ohio apples, and when I come back to Ohio, they follow
that certainly they follow that law. אלא אמר רב אשי, Ela amar
Rav Ashi, that's not what's going on. Here's what Rav Ashi says.
בפלוגתא דהני תנאי, B'plugta d'hanei tanna'ei, the debate of the following Tanna'im
that we taught in the Mishnah. הכובש שלשה כבשין בחבית אחת. Hakoveish
shlosha kvashin b'chavit achat. You are pickling three different types of vegetables
in one barrel, like you know now, you go over to Zushis,
you get right all these what is it, these mixed pickled vegetables,
right, a little cauliflower, a little whatever, you know? So all three
different types of vegetables pickled together. Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
omer, now,
one or two of them are no longer available out in the
field, but the third one is. Can you eat from this pickled
mixed mixed or not? Okay, or do you have to do ביעור
Biur and get them and you know, distribute it out to the
to the poor?
You can eat them at once, certainly that one, right?
Well, how about the fact that it has the טעם Ta'am of
the others because they're all being pickled together, so there's a transfer
of taste. Okay, so there's a three-way debate about what you do
about this.
רבי אליעזר אומר אוכלין על הראשון. Rabbi Eliezer omer ochlin al harishon.
You can only eat them as long as the first one, meaning
as long as every single one of them is still allowed to
be eaten. As soon as one of them can no longer be
eaten because it's no longer available to the animals out in the
field, then you can't eat any because it has the taste is
mixed of the whole barrel and you have to go ahead and
distribute all of this fruit. By the way, I should say Rashi
says what you do at ביעור Biur is you put it out
there for the animals to eat. Tosafot quotes ירושלמי Yerushalmi and other
sources that basically say that no, you actually call your neighbors and
you call the poor people and you distribute it, you know, you
don't keep it in your home protecting it for yourself, but it's
more the ethos of שביעית Shevi'is is that you distribute it to
everyone. Anyway, okay, so that's what Rabbi Eliezer says. It all go
as soon as one is a problem, they're all a problem.
רבי יהושע אומר אף על האחרון. Rabbi Yehoshua omer af al ha'acharon.
No, you can keep on eating as long as one of them
is still allowed. Now Tosafot says we would never say this by
normal איסור, Issur, right? If I have three things in my barrel
and one of them is חמץ, Chametz, oh so but the other
two I'm allowed to eat, I can eat all three, right? You
would never say something like that. But the point is this is
not like forbidden food, right? Because you if you bring the food
out and distribute it to the poor, they're allowed to eat from
it. You can even eat from it with them once you renounce
it and give it and give it to everybody to eat. So
it doesn't follow the normal הלכות Halachot about forbidden food and the
taste is makes other things forbidden. And as long as you don't
have to get rid of one of them, you can treat it
as a whole entity and say I don't have to get rid
of the whole thing because at least there's one thing in here
that I don't yet have to get rid of. That's what Rabbi
Yehoshua says. רבן גמליאל
אומר כל שכלה מינו מן השדה יבער מינו מן החבית. Rabban Gamliel
omer kol shekala mino min hasadeh yeva'er mino min hachavit. Anything that's
no longer available out in the field, you have to get out
of the barrel. So how is he saying different than the first
opinion? Because he's saying once you actually get the ביעור Biur out,
once you take out let's say all of the pickles, right because
there's no longer cucumbers, you're allowed to still keep the pickled tomatoes
even though the pickled tomatoes got the taste of the cucumbers. So
you don't have to worry about taste. You have to get the
actual vegetables themselves out of the barrel that have to be distributed,
but the rest you can keep on eating even though it absorbed
from the taste. Okay, והלכה כדבריו, V'halacha k'divarav, and we rule that
way. Now what does this have to do with the Rabbi Yehuda
in the Mishnah? So Rashi says, and this becomes a very weird
analogy, that it's not about pickling together in the barrel in the
Mishnah, but the Mishnah basically says that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
would say
that if you do if you bring it to a place that
it's still available in the field, you don't you can keep on
eating it. And what that means is as long as there's some
things still available in the field, you can keep on eating what
you have, even if it's not the same as what's available. You
brought your apples. Apples are no longer eaten in this place. Okay,
but since oranges are still available out in the field, you can
still keep on going and eating your apples. Similar to the idea
as long as one of the things in the barrel is okay,
everything is okay. Of course it's different, there it's all a barrel
and one unit. Here anyway, and Rabbi Yehuda says no, you say
to the guy, look, try to find apples. You won't find apples
out there, so you can't eat apples here. So tries to make
it as Okay, גמרא *Gemara* says רב פפא אמר פלוגתא דהני תנאי
*Rav Papa amar pelugta de-hanei tana'ei*. The debate of רבי Rebbe יהודה
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* and the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* is following the
following debate of תנאים
*Tannaim*. תנן *Tnan*, אוכלים בתמרים עד שיכלה האחרון שבצוער *ochlim betmarim ad
she-yichleh ha-achron she-be-Tzoar*.
You can eat dates until the very last date is no longer
available on the trees in צוער *Tzoar*, which is עיר התמרים *Ir
Hatmarim*, okay, where it was, so basically until the very last date
is no longer available on the very last palm tree. Okay, even
if in your immediate location there are no longer dates, it's not
a problem. רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* אומר *omer*, why is that? Because
we go by large regions. We'll discuss in a minute how large
of a region is defined as a region, okay? But basically anywhere
within, what does it mean it's no longer available? No longer available
in my one square mile, in my country, in my city? So
here we'll talk about that in a minute, but if in your
region it's available, even if not in your immediate locale. רבן גמליאל
*Rabban Gamliel* אומר אוכלים על שבין הקישין ואין אוכלים על שבין השיצין
*omer ochlim al she-bein ha-kishin ve-ein ochlim al she-bein ha-shitzin*. You can
still eat by virtue of things that are found, the dates when
they fall off will fall onto other leaves of the palm tree
and be suspended there. So if there's still dates on those leaves,
then you can keep on, it's considered that they're still available out
in the field and you can keep on eating them. But if
the dates have fallen off the leaves and the only dates to
be found are the ones that are at the bottom of the
tree that are between all of the thorns and thistles that grow
near the base of the tree, they're not considered to be really
available. I mean, you know, animals won't eat them because of all
the thorns and they get disgusted. So therefore you can't continue eating.
So what is that debate? So he says that the תנא קמא
*Tanna Kamma* says as you can keep on eating as long as
there are dates anywhere, even if the dates are only among the
thorns. And רבי יהודה Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says no, you say go
try to get them, since they can't be gotten easily in the
thorns, then you're not allowed to continue eating. So again notice now
we're not debating a question of מנהגים *minhagim*, following your own מנהגים
*minhagim*, following these מנהגים *minhagim*, we're debating a question about שמיטה Shmita.
*Shmita*. When is the produce still considered to be found in the
field? According to the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*, it's found in the
field only as long as the dates are on the leaves, and
according to רבי יהודה Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, it's found in the field
even if the dates are between the thorns. But again, it's a
totally different debate now according to the גמרא *Gemara*. Let's talk a
little bit about this issue about when can you keep on eating.
תנן התם *Tnan hatam*, we talked over there in שביעית *Shevi'it*, שלש
ארצות לביעור *shalosh aratzot le-vi'ur*. There are three regions for this question
of ביעור biur, *bi'ur*, of destroying the food because it's no longer
available out in the field. יהודה ועבר הירדן והגליל *Yehuda ve-Ever HaYarden
ve-haGalil*. Judea, the Transjordan, and the Galilee. Okay, ושלש ארצות לכל אחת
ואחת *ve-shalosh aratzot le-chol achat ve-achat*, and there are three subdivisions of
each one of those. I'll get back in a minute to what
that means. דלמה אמרו שלש ארצות לביעור *delama amru shalosh aratzot le-vi'ur*,
for what purpose are they saying that there are three basic regions,
יהודה *Yehuda*, גליל Galil. *Galil*, and עבר הירדן *Ever HaYarden*? שאוכלים בכל
אחת ואחת עד שיכלה האחרון שבה *she-ochlim be-chol achat ve-achat ad she-yichleh
ha-achron she-bah*. Because you can eat in all of יהודה *Yehuda* or
in all of גליל Galil. *Galil* as long as there's somewhere in
יהודה *Yehuda* that there are still dates, you can eat anywhere else
in יהודה *Yehuda*. As long as there's somewhere in the גליל *Galil*
that there are still dates, you can eat dates anywhere else in
the גליל *Galil*. So that's like the גמרא *Gemara* before about צוער
*Tzoar*. As long as there are dates on the palm trees in
צוער *Tzoar*, you can eat in the entire region, okay? So you
don't go by your immediate locale, you go by the entire region.
Okay, מנהני מילי *mena hani mili*? Where do you get this idea
that A, you have to get rid of them, and B, the
idea that you can define these big regions? So אמר רב חמא
בר עוקבא אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא אמר קרא *amar Rav Chama
bar Ukva amar Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina amar k'ra*, the פסוק *pasuk*
says, ולבהמתך ולחיה אשר בארצך asher be'artzecha, *ve-livhemtecha ve-lachaya asher be-artzecha*, that
the food of the שמיטה Shmita *Shmita* should be for your animals
and to the wild animals in the field. כל זמן שחיה אוכלת
מן השדה *kol zman she-chaya ochelet min ha-sadeh*, as long as it's
available to the wild animals that are foraging for themselves, האכל לבהמה
שבבית *ha'achel li-vhema she-be-bayit*, you can keep the food in your house
and be feeding your domesticated animals, because your domesticated animal and the
wild animal have to be on the same plane
for availability. כלה לחיה שבשדה *kalyah la-chaya she-ba-sadeh*, once it's not available
in the wild for animals, כלה לבהמתך מן הבית *kalyah li-vhemtecha min
ha-bayit*, you have to get it out of your house, you can
no longer be holding onto it and feeding it to your animals
in the house. So גמירי *gemiri*, so that's a general rule. Now
what about this idea of יהודה *Yehuda* and גליל *Galil* and עבר
הירדן *Ever HaYarden*? We have a tradition, דאין חיה שביהודה גדלה על
פירות שבגליל ודאין חיה שבגליל גדלה על פירות שביהודה *de-ein chaya she-bi-Yehuda
gedela al peirot she-ba-Galil ve-da-ein chaya she-ba-Galil gedela al peirot she-bi-Yehuda*, that
the animals observe the, you know, the political
boundaries, okay? So the animals in יהודה *Yehuda*, if they're no dates
in one place of יהודה *Yehuda*, they'll go roaming to other places
of יהודה *Yehuda*. So as long as somewhere in יהודה *Yehuda* there
are dates, you can keep on eating. But they won't go roaming
to places in גליל *Galil*, so therefore you can't eat on the
basis of what's going on in גליל *Galil*, you can only eat
on the basis of what's going on in all the places of
יהודה *Yehuda*. Now what by the way are the three subdivisions? So
there רש"י *Rashi* does say it means... There are three sub-areas but
they don't really הלכה matter. All that matters is is that it's
all יהודה or it's all גליל. So if it does say they
don't matter, why did he mention it? So תוספות says actually the
three different areas are
mountains, valleys, and fields. And that we're actually saying is in addition
to it being true that all יהודה's one, it's only true if
you go from mountain to mountain, or from valley to valley, or
from field to field, okay, that you can't actually say that because
there's, you know, dates in the valley, that it should allow me
to eat if I'm living on a hill. Okay, that those are
actually also differences that have to be observed as well. תנו רבנן,
Tanu rabanan, let's read a little bit more. פירות שיצאו מארץ ישראל
לחוץ לארץ מתבערים בכל מקום. Peirot sheyatze'u me'eretz yisrael lechutz la'aretz mitbar'im
bechol makom.
If you're bringing your fruit from ארץ ישראל to חוץ לארץ, chutz
la'aretz. and then it comes to time of the ביעור, biur you
have to get rid of them even if you are in, you
know, you're in חוץ לארץ. Okay, so you go ahead and if
you're now in Cincinnati, so you have to distribute them in Cincinnati.
שיהיו בכל מקום שהם שם. Sheyei bechol makom shehem sham. רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר אומר יחזרו למקומם. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer yachzeru limkomam.
No,
you have to be back on the plane, fly back to Israel,
and get distributed them in Israel. Okay, because right, and they should
be destroyed. משום שנאמר בארצך. Mishum shene'emar be'artzecha.
It says אשר asher. בארצך, be'artzecha so it would have to be
available to the animals of Israel. So the idea of making it
available in Israel, not just getting it out of your possession, it's
also where it's going. Okay, so the גמרא says הא אפקתיה? ha
afiktei? So one minute, you already used בארצך be'artzecha to tell you
that you have these large regions of יהודה and גליל. How can
you use it to teach this? קרי ביה בארץ בארצך. Kari bei
be'eretz be'artzecha. No, if it had said בארץ be'eretz it would have
told me one principle, that you have to go by large regions,
בארצך emphasizes this idea also that where you have to do the
ביעור is in the land. אינמי מאשר
בארצך, Inami me'asher be'artzecha, the extra word of אשר. Anyway, we learned
both principles. According to him though, you have to go back and
distribute them in Israel. Now we have a great story. רב ספרא
נפיק מארץ ישראל לחוץ לארץ. Rav Saphra nafik me'eretz yisrael lechutz la'aretz.
So רב ספרא Rav Saphra was leaving from Israel to חוץ לארץ.
הוה בהדיה גרבא דחמרא דשביעית. Hava ba'ahadei garba dechamra deshivita.
He had with him a flask of wine of שמיטה. Okay. לוו
בהדיה רב הונא בריה דרב איקא ורב כהנא. Lavu bahadei Rav Huna
brei deRav Ika veRav Kahana.
So he was being accompanied by these two rabbis, רב הונא בריה
דרב איקא Rav Huna brei deRav Ika and רב כהנא. Rav Kahana.
אמר להו, Amar lehu, and he realized oh my god, I just
left Israel and I have this flask of wine of שמיטה wine,
what am I supposed to do with it? So he said to
them, איכא דשמיע ליה מיניה דרבי אבהו, ika deshamia lei minei deRabbi
Abbahu, have you heard from רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abbahu, who was his
רבי, whether we say הלכה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר או לא. halacha
keRabbi Shimon ben Elazar o lo. Do we rule like רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, do I have to now go
back to Israel to get rid of it? Or do we not
rule like him and I can get rid of it here? אמר
להו רב כהנא, Amar lehu Rav Kahana, רב כהנא Rav Kahana said,
הכי אמר רבי אבהו, hachi amar Rabbi Abbahu, here's what רבי אבהו
Rabbi Abbahu said, הלכה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר. halacha keRabbi Shimon ben
Elazar. We rule like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar,
I'm sorry, we got to turn around and go back to Israel.
אמר להו רב הונא בריה דרב איקא, Amar lehu Rav Huna brei
deRav Ika, so the other one said, רב הונא בריה דרב איקא
Rav Huna brei deRav Ika said, הכי אמר רבי אבהו, hachi amar
Rabbi Abbahu, excuse me, I have a different tradition, here's what רבי
אבהו Rabbi Abbahu says, אין הלכה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר. ein halacha
keRabbi Shimon ben Elazar. You forgot the word אין. ein. Okay. So,
we don't rule like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar,
so you don't have to go back. So which one do you
think רב ספרא Rav Saphra was more interested in here? אמר רב
ספרא, amar Rav Saphra, נקיט כללא דרב הונא בידך. nakit klala deRav
Huna beyadcha. You know what, we should follow what רב הונא Rav
Huna is saying, that he says that he heard from רבי אבהו
Rabbi Abbahu is we don't rule like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar. Why? דדייק אגמרא שמעתא מפומיה דרביה. Dedaik agmra shamata
mipumei derabeih. He is very precise to get
the teaching straight from the mouth of his רבי. So you know,
you could hear the word אין, ein, right, is a word you
could swallow, right? Did you say do or don't, or whatever, you
know, is or isn't. So he's very clear to hear exactly what
the רבי said. And he heard the word אין הלכה, ein halacha,
we don't rule like it. טרכא דפומבדיתא. Terachta depum badita. He's as
precise as רכטא Rachta from פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. דאמר רכטא אמר רב יהודה,
De'amar Rachta amar Rav Yehuda, and רכטא Rachta in the name of
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, הר הבית אצטבא כפול הוה. har habayit istav
kaful hava. The Temple Mount was a double אצטבא. istav. אצטבא לפנים
מאצטבא, Istav lifnim me'istav, a אצטבא istav inside of a אצטבא. istav.
So somehow that he got the exact wording like אצטבא כפול, istav
kaful, you know, which is a weird phrase. So at least he's
got the last line. Okay. So anyway, so he says we have
to rule like him because he gets the, he gets, you know,
he hears precisely what the רבי said. So קרי עליה רב יוסף,
karie aleih Rav Yosef, when רב יוסף Rav Yosef heard this story,
he said about that he said about him, עמי בעצו ישאל ומקלו
יגיד לו. ami be'etzo yishal umaklo yagid lo. So this is a
thing about the people going after necromancy. My people ask their staff
and their, you know, their stick and their staff will tell them,
like you know, about forecasting signs. So he reads it
ומקלו יגיד לו, maklo yagid lo, כל המיקל לו מגיד לו. kol
hameikel lo magid lo. Anybody who's lenient, that's the one he wants
to tell him. So you ask the person who you'll get the
מיקל meikel answer. So very convenient that he followed the tradition of
רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. Okay.